<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lambs government to be exalted over all in Israel ..., or, The glory of the Lord risen like devouring fire ... with an exhortation (from God) that none ... seek to physitians ... without his leadings ... / given forth in the movings (at the commandment) of the Captain of Israel, by one that followeth him, William Baily.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08623374</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08623374</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1246:12 or 1627:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lambs government to be exalted over all in Israel ..., or, The glory of the Lord risen like devouring fire ... with an exhortation (from God) that none ... seek to physitians ... without his leadings ... / given forth in the movings (at the commandment) of the Captain of Israel, by one that followeth him, William Baily.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This work found at reel 1246:12 and 1627:6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York, and Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41482:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41482:1"/>
            <p>THE LAMBS GOVERNMENT: TO BE <hi>EXALTED</hi> over all in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who is the <hi>Captain</hi> of their Salvation, whoſe Right alone it is, (in whoſe mouth is found no guile,) and not any other Birth, Spirit, Man, or Image, whatſoever. OR, THE GLORY of the LORD</p>
            <p>Riſen like devouring Fire, to ſearch out every falſe Birth, and falſe Spirit, and to conſume Anti-Chriſt with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his mouth, and deſtroy him by the brightneſs of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And this is a <hi>certain Sound</hi> (in ſeaſon) to <hi>awaken</hi> the <hi>mixt-Multitude</hi> throughout the whole <hi>Hoſt;</hi> and that all may come to the <hi>Tryal,</hi> and ſearch and ſee, what Spirit and Birth they are of, and in what Spirit and Dominion you <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,</hi> (who are <hi>Maſters, Parents,</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> throughout all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>With an <hi>Exhortation</hi> (from God) that none within the Camp ſeek to <hi>Phyſitians</hi> (or things of that kind outward) for any diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, weakneſs, ſickneſs, or diſeaſe whatſoever, without his lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and counſel, who leadeth into all truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, That no Babe among them ſhould ſtrive, or ſtudy for the comprehending, or attaining the knowledge of the Laws of men, or Nations, to make their defence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Dear and Tender Salutation, to the bleſſed Seed and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the everlaſting, holy, Covenant of Promiſe, throughout the whole Creation.</p>
            <p>Given forth in the movings (at the commandment) of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> By one that followeth him. WILLIAM BAILY.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to receive, power, and riches, and wiſdome, and ſtrength, and honour, and glory, and bleſſing,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 5.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>For by him were all things created, that are in Heaven, and in earth, viſible &amp; invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, whether they be Thrones or Dominions, or Principalities, or Powers; all things were created by him, and for him, and he is before all things, and by him all things conſiſt; &amp; he is the Head of the Body the Church, who is the beginning, the firſt born from the dead, that in all things he might have the preheminence,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Col. 1.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41482:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41482:2"/>
            <head>THE LAMBS GOVERNMENT TO BE Exalted over all in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>JEſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God, the holy Seed, the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world (that lyes in wickedneſſe) in whoſe mouth guile is not found, whoſe name is called the Word of God, whom all are to hear, whoſe Kingdome is not of this world, whom God the Father hath raiſed from the dead, and appointed heir of all things, and Head over all to his Church, and given him a name above every name, that at his name every knee ſhould bow, of things in Heaven, and things in the Earth; and every tongue confeſſe him to be Lord, to the glory of God the Father; whom he hath given for a Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Commander of the people, in whom alone is Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Salvation, and not in any other. This is the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of thy Hoaſt, O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> this is thy King, and Law-giver; thy Judge, and Saviour; and every ſpirit, ſeed, motion, or thought, which is contrary, oppoſeth, or riſeth againſt the life of this pure, righteous, precious ſeed, (whereſoever, or in whomſoever it is, or appeareth) is of Antichriſt; which the Lord God will conſume, by the ſpirit of his mouth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy by the brightneſſe of his coming, (without reſpect of perſons): And this hath been the Teſtimony of the Servants of the Lord in Ages paſt; and this hath been, and is our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony (who are his Servants) unto the world, in this Age; which work he is now cutting ſhort in righteouſneſs, for his Elect Seeds ſake, in whom alone he is well pleaſed, which hath long been pierced, wounded, grieved and oppreſſed, by the contrary ſeed of evil doers; which have alwayes oppoſed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41482:3"/>and exalted it ſelf above all that is called God, and would not that he ſhould reign (who is the Truth, the Reſurrection and the Life), whoſe right alone it is, and for whoſe ſake the Lord God Allmighty will overturn, overturn, overturn, till he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe it unto the ends of the earth.</p>
            <p>And well ſaid the Scripture, that <hi>There are many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts in the world, and many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall deceive many; and many ſhall come and ſay, I am Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many may be deceived,</hi> &amp;c. Now this I do not onely read without in the world, but in the world which is ſet in mans heart, which hath been deceitful above all things, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately wicked; who hath ſearcht it out to the full? or who knoweth it perfectly? or who hath ſought out all its ſecret Chambers of Imagery?—Truly, I find but one right ſeed, right Spirit, Image or birth, which rightly ſeeth, and rightly judgeth all things, and ſearcheth out the moſt deep and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things, wayes, forms, ſhapes, turnings or ſpirits? It is a noble plant, a noble birth, and there is not a deeper ſpeech then it can underſtand, nor a form, that it cannot ſee, to the foundation or through the vail, to the root thereof. It is the Elect which cannot be deceived, neither will it deceive any who joyn to it, believe and truſt in it; but its not of this world, neither is its kingdome and glory of this world, but from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, (over it) in the Majeſty on high, (from whence it is born) far above the Principalities, and Powers, of the Rulers of the darkneſs of this world, (the Dominions and glory of which, are but its temptations, to draw from the more noble, into the viſible fading glory); Heaven is its Throne, and the Earth its Foot-ſtool.</p>
            <p>Therefore his Followers muſt be redeemed from the earth, from the world, the glory, the ſpirit and nature of it within, in which lyeth the ground of temptations, and the deceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe of unrighteouſneſs, and the lying wonders, and the many Antichriſts, which doth ariſe in the ſecret Chambers, againſt the appearance of this noble Seed, to ſtand in the room of it, to ſatisfie the mind, ſaying, <hi>I am Chriſt,</hi> to wit, I'le give thee ſatisfaction, I'le be thy food, thy guide, or leader, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41482:3"/>feeding the mind with falſe-hood and vanity, till at laſt it proves a falſe Prophet, which hath deceived, and caſt down many ſtrong men wounded.</p>
            <p>Therefore, Hearken O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to the voyce of the Captain of thy ſalvation, and give not heed to (nor believe) any lying vanity within or without. Neither be thou ſatisfied with a falſe Conception, or falſe birth, a falſe reſt or peace, ſhort of the Election, ſhort of the noble plant of renown, the wholly right ſeed, whoſe Kingdome is not of this world; this is the Heir, againſt which many falſe Prophets and Spirits (Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts) have riſen up, to diſpoſſeſſe him of the Inheritance. But all that go, or climb up before him, are Thieves and Robbers: therefore be watchfull and diligent, (for your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary goes about ſeeking whom to devoure) and fear always before the Lord thy God O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>believe not every ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God, for there are many falſe ſpirits and falſe births, which are not of God, but of the world;</hi> and the day of tryal is now come, in which things that have been hid ſhall be manifeſt.</p>
            <p>There is a ſpirit that can ſatisfie it ſelf, with the profeſſion, likeneſs, or image of the Truth; but its croſs and burden, is the very Truth it ſelf, which doth diſcover it, judge it, and caſt it out: Therefore take heed, and beware of that ſpirit, believe it not, but judge it in every appearance, it is the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Phariſees, which can never enter (but ſhuts up) the Kingdome of God, with all its Righteouſneſs Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and Profeſſion. This ſpirit is without the vail, and cannot ſee the end of thoſe things which God will aboliſh, being ſhut out of the Holieſt of All, in which the ſecrets, and wonderful works of God, are manifeſt to them that fear him; ſo this ſpirit judgeth according to the outward appearance, and not with righteous judgement. This is that Baſtard (or Son of the Bond woman) which ſhall not inherit with the Heir, the Son of the Free-woman. This is a knower of men after the fleſh (the fleſh is the vail) and a reſpecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and loveth the praiſe of men, and eſteemeth the rich in this world, more than the poor, whom God hath choſen rich
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41482:4"/>in faith, and heirs of his everlaſting Kingdom. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it, let it have no place in thy Boſom, or within thy Borders, O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for it is abomination unto the Lord thy God, and a great Oppreſſor and Griever of his ſeed, and a contemner, and ſecret deſpiſer of his mean appearances in his babes, and little ones, in, and by whom, he will confound the wiſdom and glory of all fleſh.</p>
            <p>Again, There is a ſpirit that thinks or conceits better of it ſelf, than of others, becauſe of outward things, which it ſeems to poſſeſſe, or becauſe of the knowledge, experiences, or try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, which it hath had in dayes paſt, through the dealings of God in his love to the Seed; and with theſe things decks it ſelfe, and through which the heart is lifted up, out of Gods fear, feeding it ſelf with the Manna which corrupteth; this is a diſobedient ſpirit, an impriſoner of the Seed and Life of God in the particular, and an oppreſſor and wounder of it in the general; and it is a lover of this world ſecretly in its heart; though it ſeems to have a beautiful out-ſide, or covering, the ſower of diſcord lodgeth (as a couched Beaſt) in its boſome: and the back-biter lyes within its breaſt, which as Arrows, it will ſend forth againſt the upright and ſimple hearted, which doth diſcover, ſee and fathome the ground and foundation thereof; therefore beware of it, judge it, and caſt it off for ever, for it is of the old leaven of malice and wickedneſs. It hath a life in giving heed to reports, (yea falſe reports) againſt others, entertaining them, and reporting them, thereby to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelf as with a garment, that ſo it might be eſteemed and have the preheminence, and that others (whom it pleaſeth) may be diſ-eſteemed, ſlighted or undervalued. This ſpirit the Lord God will caſt down, and abaſe unto the nethermoſt Pit; it is a Robber of God, and a deſpiſer of his neighbour, it is very neer unto the chains of darkneſs, in them to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, unto the day of great Judgement.</p>
            <p>Therefore O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> follow thou the Lord thy God alone, who diſcovereth the very ſecrets of all hearts, and is the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, tryer, and finder out of every falſe ſpirit, before whoſe preſence, and in whoſe ſight, all things that have been hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41482:4"/>ſhall be ſought out, evidently ſeen, and made manifeſt unto the ends of the Earth. For the day is come, in which no ſhadow of death, or dark covering, ſhall hide the worker of iniquity and wickedneſſe, though never ſo ſecret. Therefore remember with whom thou haſt to do, (for all things are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, open and bare, before his pure eyes:) And ſee thou walkeſt in the Light of the Lord, which is the Light of his true <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and remains their ſtanding dwelling-place, which ſhall be for a flame, and an everlaſting fire in the hearts of all them who wilfully and contemptuouſly tranſgreſs againſt him, and comes not to be humbled becauſe thereof, before him. This is thy God and Lord which brought thee up (at firſt) out of <hi>Egypt</hi> (the dark Land) and hath led thee by a way thou kneweſt not; who gave thee water in the deſart, and Manna in the wilderneſſe, who was as a Gloud by day, and as a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of fire by night, and who by little and little, did drive out the many ſtrange Nations, that thou mighteſt inherit the promiſed Land, which remains (for ever) a Reſt for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Seed of God.</p>
            <p>Now he called thee not out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the day of thine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and grievous burthens, ſighs, groans and tears, when thou cryedſt to go forth to ſacrifice unto him, that thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt return, or make thee a Captain, to go back again to the houſe of bondage; but that thou ſhouldſt be a redeemed, holy, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people unto himſelf, zealous for truth, righteouſneſs, and every good work. And thou mayſt remember, that thou wert charged (in that day of thy entrance into the good Land) that thou ſhouldſt not worſhip, nor bow down, to any of the Gods of the ſtrange Nations, whom he drove out before thee, neither give your ſons to their daughters, nor your daughters to their ſons in Marriage, leaſt it become a ſnare unto thee, and ſteal away thine heart, from wholly following the Lord thy God, which brought thee up from the land of darkneſs, or out of the North Country, where thou wert driven and ſcattered upon the cold, cloudy and barren Mountains, as ſheep without a ſhepherd. Was not this thy ſtate, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in which thy God ſought thee, and found thee? and was not this the acceptable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41482:5"/>year, and the appoynted time, or day of ſalvation? Didſt not thou rejoyce (as a poor captive bound in chains) to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? what wouldſt thou have promiſed, or what couldſt thou have done, or left undone, in thoſe dayes, for his ſake who then appeared for thy deliverance? Didſt thou not ſay in thine heart, that this God ſhould be thy God, if he would but give thee bread to eat, and raiment to put on, when he called thee as a woman forſaken and grieved in ſpirit, when thou couldſt have put thy mouth in the duſt, if there might have been but hope? When thou fatteſt trembling upon the ground, and lookedſt every way without for a comforter, and when thou wert as at thy wits end in thy weariſom toyls, troubles, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſpirit; then did not the Lord hear thy cryes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his Covenant, which was made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to his Seed for ever, and ſee thine afflictions, and come down to deliver? And didſt not thou rejoyce like them in Harveſt, at the appearance or breaking forth of this Morning? wert not thou ready to call in thy neighbours to rejoyce with thee, when the Lords money (on which his Image is) was found, in thine own houſe. And the ſheep that was Loſt brought home upon ſhoulders of the good Shepherd, who laid down his life for their ſakes; And when the Lord withdrew his preſence, for a little moment, was not thine heart troubled? and couldſt thou be ſatisfied, till thou hadſt found him again, whom thy ſoul lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And when thou hadſt found him, didſt thou not ſay (in thine heart) This is my beloved, this is my friend, I will hold him faſt, and not let him go, untill he hath brought me into the houſe of her that bare him, (or into the Land of reſt, in which is peace, joy, comfort, and ſatisfaction for evermore)? Didſt not thou rejoyce, when <hi>Moſes</hi> came to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> (King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Land of Bondage and Darkneſs,) and Charged him to let thee go, though it were but three dayes Journey in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Wilderneſs, becauſe of the heavy Burthens and ſore Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which thou enduredſt, under the oppreſſing Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters of the uncircumciſed? But didſt thou think what would befall thee in the Wilderneſs, the many holes, and pits, and turnings among the wild beaſts, in drought, hunger, and ſore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41482:5"/>travell? Yet how did the Lord allure thee, and then many times ſpake comfortably unto thee; And led thee by a right way, though it ſeemed hard and ſtrange unto the murmurer, and to that ſpirit which would have made a Captain, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> (that Land of Darkneſs and Bondage,) on which the plagues were poured forth, becauſe of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his ſeed.</p>
            <p>Therefore hear O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and conſider; who is a God like unto thy God? or what man was able to do theſe things which the Lord hath done for thee by his own Arme, which he ſtretched forth and revealed in the midſt of thee; who gave thee Precepts, Commandements, Statutes, and Judgements, to direct, guide, counſel, inſtruct and ſtrengthen thee in the way thou ſhouldeſt walk, which is none other, then that which firſt appeared for thy deliverance; though its Name, was then known no greater, then <hi>I AM,</hi> or the Light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> which did after become a flame, and the holy One, as a fire, to conſume and deſtroy, his and thine enemies round about; This is he who ſaid, <hi>I am God, I change not, therefore the ſons of Jacob are not conſumed.</hi> This is thy God, who commanded thee, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me, nor make, forme, or grave, any likeneſs, or Image, to bow down unto; For I the Lord thy God, am a Jealous God, and will viſit the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſins of all them that tranſgreſſe againſt my Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Therefore take heed, that thou bow not, or give thine heart, mind, and affections unto any thing, viſible or inviſible, but to the Lord thy God alone, whoſe Name is but one, and changeth not, even the Light, which makes manifeſt all things, and divides the Darkneſs from it, and hath no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull workes, and workers therein; but doth reprove them, though never ſo ſecret, <hi>and will not hold him guiltleſſe, who taketh his name in vaine:</hi> And all they who depart not from iniquity, and whoſe tongues are not bridled, ruled, or ſubjected by the power of the Lord, and who are not thereby guided, in wiſdome, meekneſs, and fear; ſuch, take the Name of the Lord in vaine, ſuch are guilty, and ſhall ſo appeare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, Angels, and men. For (as I ſaid) the day haſtens,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41482:6"/>in which no ſhadow of death, or ſecret dark place (though as deep as hell, or as high as the ſtarres of heaven) ſhall be able to hide the worker of wickedneſs, under the faireſt Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; The mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>Therefore again hear, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and repair with ſpeed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to his Tent, and none look out, but all feel and ſee the glory of the Lord God, which is like devouring fire at thy Tent door, (burning up all that which is contrary to him) that thou mayſt be preſerved, in this day of the Lords Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over; who is not onely paſſing over, but alſo through the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hearts, reines, and Conſciences of the Children of men, with his grounded Staffe; yea, even ſearching and trying to the ground, and bottom, of all foundations, and buildings; And he will fight with the contrary (the dark mountaines, the falſe foundations, and deceitfull Coverings) with Battles of ſhakings, of totterings, of ſtripings, and rentings; yea, the vaile ſhall be rent from the top to the bottom, though it be in the very Temple it ſelf, that they that have lyen in their graves, may ariſe, and come forth, and that he might appeare before the eyes of all, to be the Son of God, <hi>in whom is no guile, who humbled himſelf to the death of the Croſſe;</hi> and through it, came to Triumph over principalities, and powers, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wickedneſs, in high places. This is thy Captain, O <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> therefore think not of another, nor make another, nor forme any likeneſs of him, or of any thing, in heaven, or in earth; for there is not another whom thou art to worſhip, follow, or ſubject unto, but him alone, at whoſe preſence the vails rent, and the dead ariſe, and at whoſe Birth, and coming, the heavenly hoaſt ſing for Joy, but the Tribes of the earth mourne, <hi>(he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear)</hi> who is now come with power and great glory, in the Clouds of heaven, (not of the earth) to reward every man, equally, according to his workes, and words, without reſpect of perſons; For he is a righteous and juſt God; he is not as a man that he ſhould change, alter, or vary from what he was in the beginning, who by his power is able to raiſe up Children unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> (at this day) of them that have lyen among the pots; Therefore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41482:6"/>let your eyes look toward his holy place, whence he ariſeth, to ſilence all fleſh before him; and ceaſe from man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrills, and is as a worme and duſt before him.</p>
            <p>And know this, that thy God, who raiſed thee to be a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple above all the Families of the Earth, and hath given thee great dominion; that, if thou ſhalt exalt thy ſelf, and ſay, This thou haſt done, and the other thou haſt done, and ſecretly take the honour and glory to thy ſelf, and liſteſt thine heare up, out of the uprightneſs and integrity before him; and ſhall ſlight his mercies, and not walke humbly in his ſight, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get his wonderfull workes, and to aſcribe the glory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto his Name; That he then is able to rent the Kingdome from thee, and give thee a beaſts heart, and drive thee out to ſeed with Oxen, even among the beaſts of the field; And this God will manifeſt (on ſuch,) as he hath divers times, amongſt the ſons of men, That all fleſh may feare and tremble before him, and bow at his Name (which muſt and ſhall be exalted above every Name,) and aſcribe acknowledgments of mercy, righteouſneſs, power, and glory, unto him for evermore.</p>
            <p>For this is the ſame God, that ſet a Print upon <hi>Jobs</hi> heels, and marked all his ſteps, (whoſe Candle had ſhined upon his Tabernacle, and unto whom the Rock had poured forth Rivers of Oyl,) whom, when he came to ſee, how great and how pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, how excellent, marvailous and wonderful, the Lord was in his unſearchable wayes, he aſcribed all the righteouſneſſe to his Maker, and abhorred ſelf in duſt and aſhes, though he knew his Redeemer lived, and that he ſhould ſtand upon the earth at the latter day: Therefore take heed that thou never depart from him, (from his leadings, counſels, commandments, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and fear) who hath ſet a Print upon thine heels, and who marketh all thy ſteps, though never ſo many, or in the moſt ſecret hidden places; whether thou ſteppeſt in Butter, or upon a Rock, the Lord ſeeth all thy goings, and unto him thou muſt give an account for all thy wayes, by whom actions are weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Therefore, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Look not unto man, look not unto man, but alone unto him who is thy ſalvation, and the ſalvation of all his people to the ends of the earth. For if thou do but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41482:7"/>a little ſtand ſtill, and conſider thy ſelf, in what ſtate the Lord found thee, and how helpleſs thou wert of thy ſelf, or of any man, but by the power of God; And then again, how the Lord alone heard thy cryes, and remembred thee in the duſt, and with his own Arme brought ſalvation unto thy deſolated ſoul; I ſay, when thou Conſidereſt theſe things, in the depths of Gods Counſel, with what eye canſt thou look unto man, then with an eye that God hath opened to ſee all fleſh to be graſſe, and the glory of it as the flower of the graſſe; when the Spirit of the Lord bloweth upon it, it ſoon fadeth away. So unto him, who commanded Light to ſhine out of darkneſs, and gave light into thy dwellings, let every ſoul within thy Camp, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> be ſubject; and aſcribe all Glory; for he is the firſt, and he is the laſt, and beſides him there is no God, that is able to deliver thy ſoul from death, and thy feet from falling. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning Government in Families,</hi> &amp;c,</head>
               <p>AND now hear, O ye Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even all you, who are Maſters, Parents &amp; Governours of Familyes, or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of children, and young people. This is the word of the Lord unto you all; take heed to your own ſpirit, and ſee in and with what ſpirit you rule and govern; for all who are not in the Spirit of the Lord, cannot ſerve him, nor be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him in their ſeveral places, and amongſt their ſeveral Familyes, Tribes, and Congregations; unto whom every particular muſt give account of his Stewardſhip: Therefore ſee that ye walk and live, and rule in the Spirit, power and Wiſdom of God, in the ſtill, quiet, and cool ſpirit; in which every thought is weighed, and judged; and in it watch for the Seed, and its appearance when it ariſeth in them all, amongſt whom ye are placed, and reprove, exhort and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect in the Dominion of God, and in the Wiſdome, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and in due time and ſeaſon, even in the feeling of the Leadings of the Seed of God in your
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41482:7"/>ſelves. And for the Seeds ſake, and the Lords ſake, (who ſearcheth your hearts) and wait for the raiſing of it up, in all your Familyes, that it may be Head and Ruler, in and among you all; that the bleſſings of the Lord God may be upon you, and his preſence may bleſs your Familyes, that ye may be a bleſſing and refreſhment one to another, and be refreſhed one in another, even in the Love and Life of God, which is but one in all. And rule not with rigor, for that ſavours of the Land of darkneſſe: Nor in a wrong Dominion, in conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſelf-willedneſs, or in an impatient brittle ſpirit, but in the Wiſdom of God, which is firſt pure, then gentle and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; in his fear and dread, and in love and meekneſs, and in uprightneſs of heart and mind, as in Gods ſight, doing all things as unto him, <hi>(who ſeeth in ſecret, and will reward openly);</hi> For the Seed is ſoon oppreſſed, and the evil is ſoon ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by a wrong Government, out of the true Wiſdom, in the wrong Authority; and it will cry to God in Servants and Children, when it is grieved and oppreſſed, and God will hear it; and it will witneſſe againſt ſuch Parents, Maſters, Rulers, or Governours, as do not anſwer it in the Wiſdom and Love of God, in their Ruling, and Governing, Reproving, or Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting; for it is the even Ballance that will let them ſee and feel, (as well as you) when the weight is ſhort, or when it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds in all your words, actions, and carriages; and then the evil being preſent, it will take advantage thereby, and an hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtubbornneſs will encreaſe, in and among them, and a liberty and ſtrength in all manner of evill, when the witneſs of God is not anſwered, and the ſeed raiſed, which would ſcatter all ſuch things.</p>
               <p>Therefore great is your Charge (who are Maſters, Parents, and Governours of Familyes) and great ſhould be your care and diligence, for the ſuppreſſing and keeping under the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and wild nature, and the cheriſhing and ſtrengthning the good part, in all your Familyes, from the leaſt to the greateſt: For that is Gods, who will call you to account, how you have anſwered it, and been careful, that you have not hurt the leaſt appearance of it: And whether you have been as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41482:8"/>tender of it, as the Apple of your eye, for ſo is it unto the Lord, who will plead its cauſe with all its Oppreſſors and Grievours, (within and without) without reſpect of perſons.</p>
               <p>And when you exhort, admoniſh, or correct them, or find a cauſe ſo to do, then wait you upon God, to feel his preſence and Seed to lead, govern and go before you; that Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus may be your Head, and have the preheminence, and the Government upon his Shoulders (whoſe Right it is) in all things. And let your words be few, ſeaſoned in the ſavour of the Power, and pure, gentle, wiſdom of God, cool, quiet, and low, and not loud and clamorous, heady, or wilfull, for that ſavours of the fooliſh woman, whoſe feet are without, which buildeth not her houſe, but puls it down with her hands, but the wiſe, buildeth it up, to the praiſe and glory of God. So let Chriſt (whom you profeſſe) be known, and exalted Head, in, and among, and over you all, even the power and wiſdom of God. Then will the Lord be honoured, and the Seed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and the evil be kept under, by him whoſe right it is onely to Reign and Govern, among the children of men. And take heed that for want of watchfulneſs, circumſpection and wiſdom, ye do not diſcourage the tender appearance of truth and ſobriety in your Children, or Servants, or any under your Government; by reproving before others, or out of due time, for that may, and will, hurt and grieve the Seed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get evil thoughts, ſtubbornneſs, and an anſwering again, which will ariſe in the corrupt part, which cannot ſtraightway be juſtly reproved, becauſe there was want of the right Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Wiſdome, and diſcretion, in the Reprover; though ſomething was reproveable, yet the want of a due and right management thereof, will ſtrengthen the bad (with a witneſs) againſt the error in the Reprover. And ſo here the work is not rightly done for God, in your places, neither can it, without Chriſts leadings and guidance therein, who is the wiſdome and power of God, out of which there is nothing done, right ſerviceable, or acceptable unto the Lord; but in it, the heart is made wiſe, to diſcern both time and judgement.</p>
               <p>And take heed, ye do not ſecretly ſeek to bear rule over
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41482:8"/>others by your means, or becauſe you have more of this worlds goods, (which is all of the earth, and returns to the earth from whence it came,) for that is the leaven of the falſe Prophets, and falſe ſpirit, againſt which the woes are pronounced, becauſe it is an oppreſſor and ſecret perſecuter of the Seed. And God will abaſe that ſpirit (where ever it is) even in the ſight of men, and bring it into ſhame and contempt. For it ſecretly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth perſons, (deſpiſing the poor, and admiring, or extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the rich in this world. And thou who doſt ſo, (whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art) ſhall come into poverty, and want, and be contemned and diſ-eſteemed, and caſt out from amongſt the children of him, who had not whereon to lay his head, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou repenteſt and be humbled before his Throne) For what haſt thou? or what art thou more than another? either inward or outward, which thou haſt not received, or haſt by permiſſion (to try thee) from the Righteous God? to whom thou muſt give account, who will change times, ſeaſons, and the ſtate of things, People or Nations, as he pleaſeth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be low, and fear before him: For he will ſmite all the proud, covetous, and hypocrites, with an irreſiſtable ſtroak, whoſe wayes are an abomination unto him.</p>
               <p>Neither be thou ſelf-conceited, or lifted up in thy thoughts, becauſe thou haſt known more, or been convinced longer than others, or haſt done more, or endured, or ſuffered more than others have, leaſt the evil eye (ſpoken of) thou come to ſee with, and thy light be turned into darkneſs: For God can &amp; wil do what he pleaſe with his own; <hi>And many that are firſt, ſhall be laſt, and the laſt ſhall be firſt</hi> (as it is written). Therefore bleſſed is the man or woman that dwels in the ſenſe of Gods mercies, and their own nothingneſs, inability and weakneſs; For this ſhuts out the Phariſee, that would ſhut up the Kingdome, which will not enter it ſelf, nor ſuffer that which would. So my Friends, Remember, he enjoyed the Kingdome who was little in his own eyes; but when diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience prevailed, the Dominion was loſt, and condemnation and trouble came over that which had diſobeyed. And this is juſt and right with God, who doth and will render unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41482:9"/>one according to their words and works. Therefore dwell low, dwell little in your own eyes, as the little Child, (for of ſuch is the Kingdome of God, and ſuch onely have the Right, Authority, Dominion, and Throne, given them of God, for ſo it pleaſeth him;) And in this ye will anſwer, and reach to the ſeed of the Kingdome in all your Familyes, and in all People. Here ye will not hurt the tender, nor break the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reed, neither ſtrengthen, nor countenance the wild, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, and froward in their wayes; but your very life will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, though not a word be ſpoken. Here you Rule (in the true Dominion of the Lamb) over the Beaſts of the Field, the Fowles of the Air, and the Fiſhes of the Sea, as it was in the beginning, in the Image of God, in the bleſſed ſtate; in which dwelling and being good examples, ye will teach more in one hour, than a thouſand words every day in a whole year without it, and the witneſs of God will ariſe in them, to juſtifie you in the one, and to judge and condemn you in the other.</p>
               <p>Therefore take heed with what ſpirit you Rule in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyes; for if Chriſt be not Head, then is that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, which he will conſume, and deſtroy by the ſpirit of his mouth, and by the brightneſs of his coming: And if he be not your Head, Lord and King (who rides meekly upon the wilde Aſſe Colt) in the particular, who are Governours or Maſters of Familyes; how then are your Familyes his Familyes? and how are you of his houſhold, if Chriſt Jeſus be not the Houſholder or Governour in and among you? And how are you then of his Church, if he be not the Head, and Ruler, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor and Leader of you in all things, (who is the Leader of his People <hi>Iſrael?</hi>) Conſider theſe things (my Friends) for of the Lord am I conſtrained to write them, for his holy Seed and Name ſake, and for his Truth and the ſouls of People ſake, which are greatly oppreſſed, grieved and vexed, by a wrong Government among Children, Servants, People and Nations. And let none be ſecure or careleſs, without the feeling of the pure preſence of God, leading and guiding them in wiſdom, love, and peace, which keeps the Heart and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41482:9"/>Affections alive, unto the Lord God of Truth (whoſe Throne is Heaven) and dead to the Earth, dead to the world, and the things of it; for who comes to be careleſſe, and at eaſe in the fleſh, little regarding thoſe things before mentioned (even Gods name and Seed in themſelves, and others) are bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to ſuch, who are young, ſimple, and tender, and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks to ſuch as are to be gathered, in this day of Gods mighty power, in which he will plead with all fleſh, without reſpect of perſons; who will remove the Candleſtick of them that have forſaken their firſt love, except they ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and do their firſt works; and will ſpue the luke-warm out of his mouth, (as loathſome and burthenſome unto him). And this is the Word of the Lord unto ſuch, whoſe zeal will perform it; and the day is at hand, in which he will come quickly, and fight againſt them with the ſword of his mouth.</p>
               <p>Therefore let all be awakened, and ſee where ye are, and what ſpirit ye are of, and how the work of God goes on in the particular, and amongſt you; and whether your affections be on things above, and not on things of the earth; and whether your life is in Chriſt, the Seed, the Truth of the Moſt High God, and whether you follow the Lamb, in whom is found no guile, whitherſoever he leadeth; If you do, then are ye the wiſe Virgins with the oyle in your Lamps, ſeeing with the ſingle eye, as God ſees, who is no reſpecter of perſons, who hath choſen the poor of this world <hi>rich in faith,</hi> (mark, rich in that which purifieth the heart, and gives victory over the world, which juſtifieth in Gods ſight) and heires of his everlaſting Kingdome: Then you love in the love of God, which is unfeigned; Then you judge all things as God judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in his infallible righteous judgement, and not before or without him, who is Lord and Head over all, to his Church. Friends, I preach the Croſſe unto the world, and to the nature, ſpirit, and wayes of it (without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) in the ſenſe of what God is doing, and will ſhortly bring to paſſe, that no fleſh may glory in his preſence. And this I ſay to you all (within the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) who are of the mixt multitude, that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and yet love the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41482:10"/>Garlick; and the fleſh-pots thereof, that love the earth, and ſticks in the earth, and ſaves ſelf alive, &amp; hides from ſufferings, (for feare of loſing the earth, or your reputation among men,) you follow not the Lamb of God, <hi>in whom is no guile, who humbled himſelf to the death of the Croſſe, for the Joy that was ſet before him, who made himſelf of no reputation, and had not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to lay his head,</hi> who ſet his face like a flint, becauſe of truth and righteouſneſs, againſt all unrighteouſneſs, hypocriſie and wickedneſs whatſoever, without reſpect to the perſons of any, poſſeſſions, or places of any; For which end he was born, and for which end his followers are born, (who feel him born within them) even to witneſs for the truth, and to ſtand up upon the Earth, and plead for it; and ſuffer patiently for the Teſtimony which they hold, till the Spirit of life from God ariſe in the Conſciences of ungodly and wicked men, to plead his own Cauſe with them. You, I ſay, who are of that ſpirit, of ſelf-ſaving, you have, and ſhall have your reward, as the Phariſees had, as the mixt multitude had, and as the murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had; God gave them their hearts luſts, (ſeeing they deſired it) but ſent leanneſs into their ſouls. This is your ſtate, therefore take heed and be awakened, and retire back to the foundation of God, out of the earth; for the Lord will croſſe you, and vex you, by rolling the earth out of its place, and will abaſe your reputation, and bring you into ſhame and contempt, til you know that the Moſt high ruleth amongſt men, and governeth in the Kingdomes and Authorities amongſt men and people, who is higher then they, whoſe the Earth is, and the fulneſs of it, and not yours; you muſt give an account to him, how you have ordered it, and uſed and improved it, to the praiſe and exaltation of his Name, and the help of the true woman: For the earth and heavens are hers, and the Childs which ſhe brings forth to govern the Nations, and you are but as wormes and Graſhoppers in Gods ſight, who can cruſh you, and tread down the high places of the earth in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and rebuke and break in pieces the ſtrong Nations in a moment; and this is the Lord God of heaven a doing, that all people may fear and obey him; And theſe things are coming
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41482:10"/>to paſſe, and will be accompliſhed by him that reſpecteth not the perſons of men, but will reward every one according to his wayes.</p>
               <p>And my friends, Judgement hath begun at the houſe of God, but greater things then many have yet ſeen, are approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for a ſhort work will the Lord make on the earth, for his oppreſſed Seeds ſake, &amp; for his great Name ſake, amongſt you, and in the world; therefore expect you not great and finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to come upon the wicked without, untill the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is neerer built; For I tell you nay, you muſt firſt be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full followers of the Lamb, if you would ſee your Conqueſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Beaſt, Dragon, Whore, and falſe Prophet, (the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts) without, you muſt firſt ſee it, and your victory over the world, and the ſpirit of it (through faith and patience) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; for this way it cometh to paſſe, that no fleſh ſhould glory, but be abaſed, even to the duſt, from whence it came; And this have I ſeen, in Gods ſecret Counſell, even how he will accompliſh his great work among his people, and how he will deſtroy his and their enemies with a finall deſtruction, even like a whirlewinde when once it ariſeth.</p>
               <p>Therefore my friends, Gird up the loines of your minds, watch and be ſober, and waite alwayes upon God, and feel your hope to the end, and be not haſty, but remember the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> how the Lord was long-ſuffering, till the Ark was finiſhed, then came the Floud upon the world of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. And thus is the ſon of man come, and his long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us-ward (who obey his voyce) is ſalvation. Let him that readeth underſtand; For as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> even ſo is it now at the coming of the ſon of man; bleſſed is the eye that ſeeth, and the heart that underſtandeth, and keeps out of that eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, building and planting there ſpoken of; For much that is joyned together, muſt be ſeparated, and ſcattered, and much that is builded and planted, muſt be thrown down, and plucked up by the roots, and the earth muſt be burnt up, and the Elements melt with fervent heat; For hot will be the day, in which all the ungodly ſhall become as aſhes under the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41482:11"/>ſoles of the feet of the Saints of the Moſt high, and in which the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> ſhall be purged and purified as fine Gold; which day is but as it were begun amongſt many, but it draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neere, and haſteneth greatly; Therefore bleſſed is that wiſe ſervant that is alwayes ready waiting for his Lord, and who is giving his fellow-ſervants meane in due ſeaſon, and do not eare and drink with the drunken, nor ſmite his fellow-ſervants; for on ſuch the day will come unawares, and in an houre they think not of. And this hath the Lord God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty proclaimed, which ſhall ſound a certain ſound through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to the ends of the Earth, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So this I have written in obedience to the Lord, that I might be clear of their blood whom it chiefly concernes: and concerning whom it came into my heart from God, to lay theſe things before you; For I have deſired of the Lord, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me aright in all things according to his will, and I labour to keep my Conſcience voyd of offence toward him and all men; and I travell and pray to God, that I may finiſh my Courſe with Joy, and give up my account dayly, and at the laſt with joy, and not with griefe; And this (God knoweth) is the hearty deſire of my breathing ſoul unto his Throne for you all, that with one minde and heart, we may all preſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in the ſame way, which is the ſteps and path of the juſt one, that leads more and more unto perfection, out of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, out of the earth, out of the darkneſs, and the old leavens, into Paradiſe, where man was made a living ſoul, in the image and likeneſs of his Maker, (where the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is known, and the Bleſſings enjoyed, which makes rich, and the pleaſures at his right Hand, which laſt for ever) unto whom my ſoul aſcribeth all glory, praiſe, honour and thanks, who is worthy of all, to whom be it for ever given, by all that feel Breath in the land of the living.</p>
               <p>And now, all ye dear and tender breathing Babes and Children of the moſt high God, whoſe hearts and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings the Lord hath opened, who have caſt down all your Crowns at the feet of the Lamb, who have forſaken, and can
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41482:11"/>forſake all, for his ſake in whom is no guile, who have obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his voyce, and faithfully follow him in the Regeneration, who love not your lives unto death, for his ſake that was ſlain from the foundation of the world, becauſe of the ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his precious oyntment, which you dayly feel poured forth into your veſſels; Ye onely are the wiſe Virgins, ye are the Redeemed from the Earth, and are not defiled with women, (the weak and beggerly things.) And this is the word of the Lord God Almighty, that lives for ever unto you all; The day of your Redemption, the day of your ſitting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Thrones, the day of ſhouting and of ſinging Halelujahs for joy, is at hand, in the triumphant Dominion of the Lord God Omnipotent, over all fleſh and uncleane ſpirits, over the raging waves of the Sea, in the midſt of the greateſt ſtormes, yea, over Death and Hell, and the Gates of it, which ſhall never prevaile againſt you, as you abide on the Rock, as you inhabite the Rock; you ſhall ſing praiſes, yea high praiſes unto him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever, who is worthy to receive power, wiſdome, riches, honour, glory and bleſſings for ever and ever over all in the Higheſt, <hi>Amen,</hi> Halelujah; who giveth you the victory; Therefore faint not, for unto you this is the word of the Lord God, who liveth and reigneth for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Iſrael is commanded not to meddle with Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or Phyſitians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for any diſeaſe or diſtemper, without the Leadings and Counſel of the Lord their God,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friends;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am commanded of the Lord, and it lyes upon me, (in the fear of his Name, and in the bowels of his love) to warn and charge you whom it concerns, (that I may be cleer in his ſight) of theſe particulars following, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. All you who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41482:12"/>(in this great day of judgements and tryals within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out) feels any diſtemper, weakneſs, ſickneſs, pains, or any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe whatſoever;—Seek not to Phyſitians, without Gods eternal motion, or in the clear freedome of his life, nor let out your minds in an eager ſeeking a remedy to any man, people or things outward, but as the living God alone guides you, who is a preſent help in time of trouble, to all his children that wait upon him: And know ye this for a ſurety, that the Lord our God hath made known the Tree of Life again (unto his babes that fear him) which is in the midſt of the Paradice of God, whoſe vertue heals within and without, bleſſed and praiſed be his holy name for evermore: Therefore all ye who profeſſe the knowledge of God, and faith in Jeſus Chriſt, now try your ſelves and your faith, concerning theſe things, for if you truly know God, and Chriſt (whom he hath ſent, to be a Prince and a Saviour,) and your faith ſtands in the power of God (and not in a ſound onely) then you know the Tree of Life, and him that gives us life and breath, and all things: Mark, and if he gives us all things, then he gives wiſdom, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and counſel to his people, in all things needful, how to walk, act, or ſpeak in all occaſions, and at all times and places, (who guides the meek in his way, and teacheth the humble in judgement.) Therefore I ſay, wait you upon God alone, in the pure fear of his name, for counſel and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in this particular, if you love the peace of your own ſouls, and ſeek not any thing for a remedy, but in his leading, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and wiſdome, and in the faith of Gods Elect; for if you do, it will adde to your trouble, and ſorrow, and diſtemper; its the Word of the Lord unto you, which you will know ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in the end.</p>
               <p>Therefore my dear Friends, Dwell in the Light, which makes all things, ſtates, and conditions manifeſt; and wait upon the Lord in the ſtill, cool, and quiet ſpirit, for the right underſtanding of your own particular ſtate, and the ground and cauſe of all diſtempers, diſeaſes, or judgements, in your own particulars; elſe how are you as the ſpiritual man, that judgeth all things, if you know not the things of God, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41482:12"/>what is in man, and the ground of all diſtempers, diſeaſes, and judgements? where is your dwelling with him that is greater than <hi>Solomon,</hi> if you know not that wiſdome, which gives the underſtanding of all things, from the Hyſop on the wall, to the Cedar in <hi>Lebanon?</hi> how can you be wiſer than Serpents? or how will you know the ſuries of wilde Beaſts, and that which bounds and limits them, if you know not the ground of all things in your own particulars?</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſay again, Wait upon the Lord of life, and think not your time miſ-ſpent in ſo doing; neither give your ſelves reſt till you in very deed know Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Tree of Life in the midſt of the Garden of God. For I muſt ſay in the word of the Lord, many may be deceived with the apprehenſion, or a name to live, and may profeſs and talk of him, and yet be dead and ignorant of the true and right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, and his wayes; to whom he will profeſſe, he never knew them. Oh! that this fearful day and ſentence may never ſurprize any of you, who have taſted that the Lord is gracious. For many people have been deſtroyed for lack of knowledge, and of a right underſtanding in theſe things before mentioned, not knowing the intent of the motions of Gods Spirit within them, neither diſcerning the Lords body; for ſince tranſgreſſion, diſobedience, and ignorance of God (the cloud of errour and darkneſs) hath over-ſpread the world, the ground of theſe things have been hid to the children of men; ſo that when the diſpleaſure of God hath been kindled againſt them, they have not perceived it in the ground, in the particular; but were apt to talk of it in a general way, that ſin is the cauſe, (when great plagues and judgements comes upon a people,) or the like; but ſcarce one man in a Nation, did turn in his mind, and wait upon God, to ſee his will and counſel in ſuch things, in the particular; but ſuch as did, (and obeyed the Lord) were Prophets, who cryed againſt ſuch things in the general, as they had ſuffered the indignation of the Lord for, (who had ſubdued them) in the particular. And ſo the Lord God hath often ſent his viſitations amongſt the children of men, and his Servants to warn them, that they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41482:13"/>might be awakened, and repent, and be humbled before him, that ſo he might ſhew them his way, and guide them in it, (which is a way of holineſs, mercy and truth;) and that they might alway fear and dread his great Name, and terrible Majeſty, (who is able to do whatſoever he will in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and in the Earth) and that they might (through his judgements) come to be redeemed, and reconciled unto him in Chriſt, the everlaſting Covenant of life and peace.</p>
               <p>Therefore my dear Friends, Wait you upon God, and let him be your fear and your dread, then will you not dread man, or (rather) the furies of wilde Beaſts, or Serpents, which is manifeſt in the ſons of men; neither let in the fear of death or any tryal whatſoever, which tends to the vailing, or weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your tender life, which you have felt and enjoyed in God; but let the preſence of the Mighty God of worm <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> fill your hearts, (who is able to deſtroy both body and ſoul in hell, and alſo to ſave to the uttermoſt all them that fear and obey him,) that you may feelingly and perfectly know and underſtand (in the light of the Lord) all things that comes to paſſe in your particulars; then ſhall you be of a right and ſound judgement, concerning all men, ſpirits, and things in the general; for none can truly know the Cauſe, Ground, or Root of a matter, originally, but who dwels in God, the Root that bears him (and all men), the original of life; and he that doth not know aright, may eaſily or ſoon judge wrong. Therefore its the Saints onely, (amongſt all the children of men) that are able, and can, and muſt judge the world: Mark, (who are ſanctified by Chriſt Jeſus,) yea, ſuch ſhall judge An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels who dwell in him, to whom they all bow; for he is judge of quick and dead, and from him is no ſecret hid, that ſhall not be manifeſt, <hi>For he is come neer to judgement, (and is a ſwift witneſſe againſt all unrighteouſneſſe) and alſo his tender mercies and bleſſings, are neer the upright-hearted, which is to them as the former and latter rain; but the rebellious dwell in a dry Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So be you all very ſtill in your minds, and not will, or run, but diligently heed the will and counſel of the motions of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41482:13"/>Gods good Spirit in you, (which is the onely Teacher of his people,) for he hath ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with man;</hi> and he is the true Phyſitian, Shepherd, and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer of the ſoul; and will he not over-ſee and take care for the body (the leſſer) by giving wiſdom and diſcretion how to order all his creatures to his praiſe? yea, and this is witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among his babes, bleſſed and praiſed for ever be his name, which is their ſtrong Tower and Safety, Rock and Defence; and they need not another, who are come to dwell in the <hi>Holy City, New Jeruſalem that came down from God, the quiet habitation, whoſe walls are peace, and gates praiſe and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; here is no need of Candle, Sun, or Moon to give light, but the Glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> And hither is the Lord God of endleſs wiſdom and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, bringing his little ones, that beleeve and truſt alone in him, who is becoming all in all, in his faithful children; this is the ſum (my Friends) this is that we have waited for, to which end the Lord hath long waited to be more and more manifeſting his grace and wiſdome unto us, that we might come up hither by deſcending lower in our ſelves, into him who is the root, and off-ſpring; what ſhall I ſay of him? if it can be born, I could ſay much in the infallible counſel of God, that he is becoming the Father and Mother, Feeder and Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Healer, Guider and Governour, yea, all, (as I have ſaid) unto his dear Lambs, who have long breathed, and pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after him, and cannot be fully ſatisfied till this is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed: No borrowed light, no Moon or Candle, will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the Noble birth, but the very glory of God, and the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Lamb, to whom it aſcribes all, having received all out of the boſome of the eternal treaſury of the wiſdom and compaſſions of the Allmighty. And ſo here is a cry heard, with a loud voyce from the Throne of God, and the Lamb, Ceaſe from man, ceaſe from man (in all things) and come up hither ye travelling children, and you ſhall be refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ſatisfied; its I have heard your cryes; and if men at any time have had compaſſion on you, it was through my bowels, which I put upon him to that end; therefore look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41482:14"/>me, and come, I am the fountain of all goodneſs, mercy, and truth, ſaith the Lord God, and not any man; for they are but as Ciſterns which may break, and then where wilt thou be for thy dayly nouriſhment and refreſhment? Theſe were the two great evils committed in the dayes paſt, <hi>viz: They have forſaken me the Fountain of living waters, and hewed them out ciſterns, broken Ciſterns, that could hold no water; for which the Heavens were aſtoniſhed and very deſolate, and afraid. Is Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael a home-born ſlave?</hi> (read <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. and conſider it perfectly, for the latter dayes of conſiderations are come) as much as if God had ſaid, Is <hi>Iſrael (who once wreſtled like a Prince, and prevailed, and had power with God, and with man,</hi> &amp;c.) become ſo ignoble, as to forſake me the Fountain, and be ſatisfied now with Ciſterns, that will hold no water? Oh! this was a horrible thing, theſe were great evils; the very Heavens were aſtoniſhed at this.</p>
               <p>Therefore my dear Friends, (let this ſaying ſink deep into your hearts,) See that you alwayes, in all things mind the Motions and Leadings of the Spirit of Truth; for it is the true and perfect Guide, ſent of the Father to guide us into all Truth, and to ſhew us things to come; and he that follows any man by word, or example, and goes from this in himſelf, hath committed a great evil, even Idolatry, and is gone from the hearkning and obeying; this is the <hi>Witchcraft</hi> ſpoken of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22, 23. &amp; <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. This is not to be ſuffered to live, or not to be lived in, in all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Exod. 22.18. the Lord hath ſpoken it; for worm <hi>Jacob</hi> (who is now ariſing in the ſtrength and pure wiſdom of his God,) is no more a home-born ſlave, to feed at Ciſterns, or live upon Husks, or to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with any likeneſs whatſoever, but is filling himſelf at the living Fountain of the Riches &amp; Nobility at the right hand of the Majeſty on high; and ſo in vain is the ſnares laid in the ſight of him that hath wings, that ſees them, and is able to eſcape them; for there is a Remnant that ſtands upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with the Lamb, in the innocent life, who are (and can freely) come to God the Judge of all, &amp; be ript open, and ſtand naked in the particular; and ſuch is the Lord God cloathing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41482:14"/>with white robes of his everlaſting Righteouſneſs, which ſhall never wax old; glory unto him in the higheſt, who hath wrought all our works, in us, and for us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So remember, the Spirit of truth is thy proper Leader, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in all things concerning ſoul and body, at all times, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and occaſions, and not any other; Nay, though an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, (ſee thou do it not) for they are but miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth for them that are heires of ſalvation, and are fellow-ſervants with them who are led by the Spirit of truth, and are not to be worſhipped, or followed any further then is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the leadings of Gods Spirit in thy own heart; for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him thou muſt give an account, and not unto Angels or men.</p>
               <p>Now I do not hereby limit the Lord, nor his people, from exerciſing their pure faith, in any thing concerning their ſtate, either inward or outward; And as for the things before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned concerning the health or weakneſs of the outward man, I do know that there are natural and accidental cauſes of weakneſs, ſickneſs, or diſtempers, which are incident even to Gods dear Children, (while in theſe earthen Tabernacles,) for which naturall things may be applyed in the leadings of the life and wiſdome of God, by which they were created; I ſay, my intent is not, (neither am I joyned to ſuch a ſpirit,) as to impoſe, or limit the motion of Gods Spirit in any thing whatſoever, but onely to limit the contrary, even the haſty minde and ſpirit, and that all may come to be guided by the Counſell of God, out of ignorance and doubtfulneſs, into clearneſs, and a perfect knowledge of their own ſtate (as it is in Gods ſight,) and of the vertuouſneſs of the power of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, of the holy Seed in themſelves; and not be led in blindneſs, and unſenſibleneſs, in which ſtate is the error and miſtakes, and wherein people are deſtroyed for lack of true and ſound knowledge; and here they have many things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed (and are apt ſo to do,) even naturall and viſible things, for ſpirituall and inviſible cauſes, I do not mean an inviſible diſtemper meerly of the outward man, which may proceed from a viſible or naturall cauſe: But when God by his Spirit,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41482:15"/>ſtrives with man, in him, and ſmites on his Conſcience, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſin, or ſome diſobedience or other, through which, the Lord beholds guilt, and cannot but puniſh, which cauſeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the countenance to change, and brings judgement upon the very creature, becauſe thereof; I ſay, this ſhall never be removed (in the ground) by any outward or viſible thing; the Lord hath ſpoken it: For it is ſtriving againſt the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and the good end of his gentle chaſtiſements with the creatures, which he hath created for his praiſe, and to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his counſell and wiſdome, by which they were all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and have their being; ſo this ignorant, wilfull, impatient ſpirit, which cannot truſt God, this is to be limited, and bound down, by the dread and power of the Lord; that the innocent Seed, (which can truſt in him,) which hath long ſuffered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der oppreſſion may ariſe; in whoſe reſurrection and life, is the healing and bleſſing of the Nations that are ſaved, which are for ever to walk in the light of the Lamb.</p>
               <p>So let all be ſubject to him, that gives life and breath, and all things, and be not haſty (when any trouble or diſtemper comes) to be delivered, or to get eaſe from under it, till thou (in patience) haſt ſeen the mind of God therein, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by him that comes out of <hi>Sion,</hi> to turn away ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from <hi>Jacob;</hi> bleſſed is the eye that ſees, and the heart that underſtands, and contrives not any thing in the will, but as led and guided by the Shepherd of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Lambs to lack any good thing for their body nor ſoul, which in his wiſdome he ſees meet for them. And that which is not ſubject, is the carnall mind, in which the enmity lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the death, trouble, and condemnation; here the Lyons lack and ſuffer hunger, but the meek ſhall increaſe their joy in the Lord, and they that wait upon him, ſhall run and not be weary, and walk and not faint.</p>
               <p>And know this for infallible truth, that whoſoever uſeth, or applieth the creatures of God, (even naturall things, which are good in themſelves and places,) to a condition not ſuitable, even when God ſmites upon the Conſcience, for any diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or wickedneſs, by which (as I have ſaid) the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41482:15"/>man comes alſo to ſuffer, being partaker with the ſpirit that tranſgreſſed, that this ſtate is parallel to that mentioned <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 22.12, 13, 14. When God called for faſting, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and mourning, behold ſlaying of oxen and killing of ſheep, &amp;c. which was iniquity that ſhould not be purged till they dye.</p>
               <p>Therefore dear friends, think on theſe things, (which are but as a touch of what might be ſpoken, (but a word to the wiſe is ſufficient) and waite upon the Lord alone to be guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all things, and do nothing haſtily out of his fear and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, which onely is known, underſtood, and ſtood in, in the ſtill and quiet waiting, in the retiredneſs of mind and ſpirit, ſtaid upon him, (out of all your own willings and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings or runnings,) in the ſinking down, and ſubjectedneſs to his holy will alone; that he might be all, in you all, and you as nothing before him, but veſſels of his honour, praiſe, and glory; to whom be it given over all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>No Babe in</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſtudy for the attaining the Lawes of men, to make their defence,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>AND my dear friends, who have no knowledge in the Lawes of men or Nations (which are in the fall) and are in ſuch things ignorant as children, this is my adviſe unto you, from my God, and your God; do not now ſtudy or ſtrive to attain the knowledge thereof, in any caſe, to make your defence, when you are brought before Rulers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours (or their Judgement-ſeats) for the Name ſake of Chriſt Jeſus; for if you do, it will prove like <hi>Sauls</hi> Armour, (which <hi>David</hi> (the Seed) cannot go out to war with) unleſs you have the knowledge of ſuch things already, (as a ſervant,)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41482:16"/>to uſe in the dominion and pure wiſdome of God; for this I have found, (who am alſo ignorant of ſuch things as a babe) That the Innocent Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> need none to plead its cauſe, but God alone, who giveth ſtrength and wiſdome in the ſame hour.</p>
               <p>Therefore my dear and tender Friends, Look not out from your own meaſures received of the grace of God, which is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; neither conſult with fleſh and blood, by reaſonings, diſputings, or premeditations; but ſtand ſingle and innocent, eying the Honour and Glory of God, in his pure fear and true humility; for in this alone is the Victory, Wiſdome and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings obtained, and God will not give it to another; for the Battel is the Lords, and we are to ſtand ſtill (in the Seed) to ſee his ſalvation; and then keeping low, this will glorifie its Father alone, as the Father hath glorified it with Dominion and Peace. And conſider what Law or Learning <hi>David</hi> had, when he came from feeding the Sheep, (being but a youth); and what weapon had he when he ſlew the uncircumciſed <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtine,</hi> more than the ſmooth ſtone in the Shepherds Bag, (he that can read, let him) without Staffe or Spear, in the Name of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And they marvailed to ſee the boldneſs of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who were ignorant and unlearned men, in their Laws and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Diſciples of Jeſus know not the Law;</hi> and alſo of him, <hi>Whence hath this man learning, ſeeing he knoweth not Letters?</hi> Thus did God confound the wiſdome of the wiſe and prudent in Ages paſt, (as in this Age) who hath alway choſen the fooliſh things of this world, that no fleſh, or fleſhly part ſhould glory in his preſence.</p>
               <p>Therefore Dear Friends, Let no Babe or ſimple one among you, be diſcouraged, who are ignorant in the outward Lawes and Letters; but keep to the Royal Law in the heart, written by the Finger of the living God, in which you will feel the ſpringings up of the Royal Seed and Birth, which fulfils the righteous Law and Letters (and was before the Letters and Lawes of men was) whoſe heart truſteth only in the living
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41482:16"/>God, and makes not fleſh his Arme. This is the true Seed, the Heir: But that which makes fleſh his Arme, is the Seed of evill doers, which ſhall never be renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>And ſo my dear Friends, in all things mind the leadings and counſel of God, for he leads his people, and guides their feet in the way of peace; and he alone is the ſaving health of all Nations, and without him they can do nothing that is good and acceptable in his ſight; and let your eyes be toward him who is inviſible, dwelling in the light; and neither act or ſpeak out of his fear and counſel; then will you be preſerved, to his praiſe, and to your eternal comfort and peace; and whether you eat or drink, or whatever you doe, let all be done in the Faith, to the glory of God, (for <hi>what is not of faith, is ſin,</hi>) ſo ſhall you be kept ſtedfaſt on the unmoveable Rock, through and over all things which may come to paſs, as your tryals; and be upheld in the meek and quiet ſpirit, which in Gods ſight is of great price: And in this is the Kingdome and patience of Jeſus, and the victory of the Lamb, known, who muſt Rule and Reigne, till all his enemies are put under his Feet. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41482:17"/>
               <head>To the Bleſſed Seed, and Children of the Everlaſting Holy Covenant, in the Life of the Lamb of God, in whoſe mouth is found no guile, throughout the whole Creation. A moſt dear and tender Salutation.</head>
               <p>O Thou Bleſſed Seed of the promiſe, who haſt long lain as in the Clefts of the Rocks, and haſt been as a ſtranger throughout the whole world, and yet lyes as a Lamb ſlain in the ſtreets of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſpiritually; my ſoul breaths, cryes, and groans unto the living God for thy ſake, and I am in ſorrow, and pain, as a woman in travel, becauſe of thy great oppreſſions; who knoweth thy ſorrows, thy griefs, and thy ſecret complaints? who knoweth thy ſighs, thy groans, and thy tears, amongſt the children of men (who art as a worm in the loweſt parts of the earth, bearing the weights and heavy preſſures of the iniquity thereof?) To whom canſt thou turn (to the right hand or left) to unboſome thy ſelf (in the depth of thy inward travels) but onely to the living fountain from whence thou ſprang? O O thou Lamb of God, which takes away the ſin, and removes the foundations of the Earth; when wilt thou yet ariſe more in thy beauty and glory among the ſons of men? to bear the Government on thy ſhoulders, whoſe right it is, <hi>That thou mayeſt lead them forth in the green paſtures, by the fountain of ſtill waters;</hi> that thy innocency, tenderneſs, and love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned, might be known as the waters cover the Sea. For thou art without guile, the alone pure, and undefiled one; thou art harmleſs as a Dove, thou art the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, thou art altogether lovely, the world knoweth thee not; thou art as a Lilly among Thorns, and as an Apple Tree
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41482:17"/>amongſt the Trees of the Forreſt; thy ſmell is as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and thy taſte exceeds the Pomgranates: O thou faireſt among the Sons, and thou beautifulleſt among the Daughters! What ſhall I ſay of thee (O thou Beloved of my ſoul?) I am even ſick of love, my ſoul is even melted in the breathings of thy precious life, and I am even raviſhed with love in thy preſence, for thy Countenance is exceeding the Angels of God; thou art terrible as an Army with Banners to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly; but thou delighteſt in the upright, humble, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ones; thou art my Saviour in whom my ſoul rejoyceth, and my ſpirit doth magnifie thee, O thou everlaſting Son of Righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Ariſe, ariſe, ſhine forth in thy ſtrength and glory, and drive back all the Clouds of darkneſſe which have covered the Earth, and the groſſe darkneſſe which hath covered the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; that the glory of thy Light may enlighten the world, and thy brightneſſe may ſhame and confound the glory of all fleſh, that thy dominion might be known throughout the whole Earth, which is an everlaſting dominion, and thy Kingdome of Righteouſneſs which hath no end; that the Nations may come to the glory of thy Light, and Kings to the brightneſſe thereof, to Rule in thine Eternal Counſel, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Dominion, and Victory over all; that ſongs of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, deliverance, and triumph, for ever and ever, may be founded unto thee, who waſt dead, and art alive, and liveſt for evermore, caſting down all their Crowns at thy feet, for thou alone art worthy to Rule and Reign, and to have all Honour, Glory, Strength, Wiſdome, Riches and Bleſſing: For thou wert ſlain becauſe of our ſins, and art now ariſing to redeem thy People out of Kindreds, Tongues and Nations, by thy blood, and art becoming King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, in us thy Babes and Children; thou art the Tree of life in the midſt of the Garden of God, by thy vertue muſt the Nations be healed; thou art the Pearl of great price, thy worth is not to be valued with fine Cold; thou art far above Rubies; thou haſt been a Treaſure hid in the field,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41482:18"/>dwelling in the lower parts of the Earth, and yet above the higheſt Heavens; both which thou haſt upheld to this day, by thy power; thou art the Salt of the Earth, and the Light of the world, though they have not known thee, but trampled thee under foot, as a deſpicable thing; thy face hath been marred more than any mans, and thy form, more than the ſons of men; thou art that Juſt One, and holy Childe, which hath long been as a Servant, though by right, art Lord of all; on thy back hath the Ploughers ploughed long furrows; oh how have the Smiters ſmitten, at the appearance of the lifting up of thy tender countenance? (When this I have conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, my ſoul hath mourned in ſecret, and mine eyes have trickled down tears, in the ſence of thy deep ſufferings;) and yet, had it not been for thy ſake, the whole world had been as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and been conſumed like unto <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> Oh who will not now come down and ſuffer with thee, that they may alſo reign with thee as Kings and Prieſts on the Earth? For now thou art ariſing in the greatneſſe of thy ſtrength, to be avenged on all thine oppreſſors. <hi>Thou haſt trodden the Wine-preſſe alone, and of the People there was none with thee:— Therefore wilt thou trample them in thy fury, and ſtain all thy Raiment; for the day of vengeance is in thine heart, and the year of thy redemptions is come.</hi> Thou art the King of <hi>Sion,</hi> thou haſt the key of <hi>David,</hi> (and the keys of Death and of Hell,) who rideſt meekly upon the wilde Aſſe Colt, as in the dayes of old. Come forth now O ye Daughters of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and behold your King, even the Lamb of God, which hath been ſlain, in whoſe mouth guile is not found, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away your ſins, and follow him for ever, ye Daughters of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and Sons of <hi>Jacob; for it is of the Lords mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy you are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions fail not</hi> toward his Seed, but remains ſure in his Covenant for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore now, all ye followers of the Lamb, be ye very ſtill, low, and watchful, dwelling in the pure dread and humility of him that ſits upon the Throne, and of the Lamb
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41482:18"/>for evermore; and let none be careleſſe or wilful, leaſt ye be found in the degeneration, from the ſpirit of the ſubjection of the Lamb of God, who is come to Rule; but in his life ſtand you upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> with him, with the Harps of his high praiſes in your hands; for they onely are the choſen and bleſſed, who are faithful followers of him in the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: So let your eye be ſingle, and your minds retired, dwelling in the good Shepherds Tent of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hid in him, whom the world knows not, where you will feel quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to your immortal ſouls, and peace and patience to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo all tryals; for this is a day of great and manifold temptations, and tryals, in which the enmity works, every way in its full ſtrength, among the children of men: but its violent force, is chiefly bent, as a mighty floud, or full current, to ſink and deſtroy the Ark of the Teſtimony of God; feel me in your life, (within and without) ye dear children, ye ſimple-hearted, breathing babes; who know the winnowings on every hand, and how the Tempter works, to draw out the mind and affections one way or other, that he might get advantage, to ſpoyle your reſting place, (which you have in the ſtaidneſſe on God, and ſimplicity of Chriſt) and to keep the ſoul and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding clouded in darkneſſe and unſenſibleneſſe, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and blindneſſe, to be luke-warm, careleſſe or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, without the feeling and preſent enjoyment of the pure refreſhing preſence of Gods Countenance; then he hath his purpoſe, (who ſeeks to devoure) for in the darkneſſe is the root of diſobedience, and every evill word, and work; then the root of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe will ſpring up, through which many may be defiled; then the ſelf-will, which is crooked and perverſe, ariſeth again; then the pure ſavour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning is decreaſed, and love waxen cold; then the tender innocent Seed ſuffers; the Lamb is pierced and wounded, which ſhould have the preheminence; then ſtrife in the high mind, out of Gods awe and dread,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41482:19"/>gets up; then the Strong Man begins to keep the houſe again, who was once bound, and his goods ſpoyled; then the meek, that ſhould ride upon the wilde Aſſe Colt, is thrown down, and trampled upon by the wilde; then <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> (the ruffe man) reign over worm <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God Allmighty keep all his Babes (who have taſted of his Heavenly gift, and of the precious vertue of the endleſſe life) out of this ſtate. My ſoul is even bowed down, and the travel of a burthen is upon me, becauſe of the deep ſufferings of the Holy Seed, and the oppreſſions of the poor, by him that is too ſtrong for him; O Lord ariſe, ariſe, and plead its innocent cauſe with all fleſh. O all ye breathing Babes of God, abide for ever in the pure ſubjection to his good and perfect will, in his fear, and in tenderneſſe of heart; then how can you but partake of the afflictions of your Brethren, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It came into <hi>Moſes</hi> heart (and that from God) to viſit his poor afflicted brethren, which cryed and groaned under the cruell and heavy oppreſſions, and God rewarded him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his works; And now, can the Seed and children there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of mourne and languiſh, or be ſorrowfull, and I not feel it? can they be tempted and tryed in the Wilderneſs, and I not ſenſible thereof? how can this be, if I be in Chriſt Jeſus, who is afflicted in all their afflictions. My friends, it is a day of mourning, of weeping and faſting, (let the wiſe underſtand) though in God I rejoyce, that my Name is written in heaven, and this is more to know, and feel, then if all the Devills without, were ſubject.</p>
               <p>Therefore ye followers of the Lamb dwell in the ſenſe and feeling of the life, of the precious, tender, ſuffering Seed, that you may know the marriage of the Lamb come, and rejoyce greatly becauſe of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes Voyce, for this makes glad the upright, and the weak to be as <hi>David;</hi> And here you will eat your own bread
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41482:19"/>from your Fathers hand, which he gives freely to the hungry ſoul, and be kept out of all ſtrife and debate, diſputings and murmurings, in the gentle contented Spirit of the Lamb, who is the ſaving health of all his people: Here you will know the place of broad Rivers, where goes no Gally with Oares, no toyl, or labour, or ſtriving, but to ſtand ſtill: Here is the beginning known, and the Glory that was before the VVorld was, or the Hills, or the Foundation of the earth were laid, (bleſſed is he that readeth in the life of theſe things): Here is the place of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, as the Munition of Rocks, where the bread is ſure, and the water never fails, but iſſueth forth from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Paradiſe of God, for evermore: Here is the lying down under the Vine, where none can make afraid: Bleſſings and thanks to him that lives for ever: Here is the returning naked, as we came into the World, (even ſo we go out,) carrying nothing, and yet poſſeſſeth all things: Here's the little child, that enters the Kingdome, even that Kingdome (of Heaven) where the leaſt is the greateſt, the loweſt is the Higheſt, the pooreſt is the richeſt, the weakeſt is the ſtrongeſt, the ſimpleſt is the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</p>
               <p>VVhere is the diſputer now? where is the gloryer in the ſtrength, wiſdome, Arts, and parts (in the ſpirit of this world) now? VVhere are the wiſe, and the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and the counter of Towers now? where is the high Profeſſor, and great talker in the ſtrong Towers of comprehenſion and Imaginations now? where are the climbers up above the Door now? Behold a little child is Governour, The poor man (which was diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded) delivered the City by (his) wiſdome: He that can read, let him; for God hath made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world, and the ſeers are blind; The ſounding braſs is empty; the ſtrong are become weak, and the weak ſaith, <hi>I am ſtrong;</hi> they that were dead, are alive, and them that were lively, are now as dead men on the Sea-ſhore; God is turning the world upſide down, the Lamb ſhall Rule,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41482:20"/>and all the Beaſts of the Forreſt ſhall fear, and bow before him; The Lilly ſhall grow higher then the Cedar, the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall ſit upon the Throne, and the Counſeller as in the beginning ſhall be known, and Judges as at the firſt; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he that readeth, underſtandeth, and enjoyeth theſe things; Gods ſalvation and Covenant of eternall life and peace, is then witneſſed, who is the good Shepherd, and true Phyſitian of his people. And this is thy Captain, O <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> who is made perfect, through ſufferings; therefore obey thou him in all things; follow him in his footſteps, who leads in the way of Righteouſneſs, that ſo thou may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the power of his Reſurrection, and poſſeſſe thy ſoul in his patience, and lye down in his eternall will, in the reſt prepared, that ſo the ſecond death, over thee, may have no power.</p>
               <p>So my dear friends, the Lord God of Life, preſerve you all faithfull, bearing your ſingle and pure Teſtimony for his holy Name, in this your day and generation, that you may be the chaſte Virgins, and entire followers of the Lamb, in whoſe mouth guile is not found, that ſo you may give up your account with chearfulneſs, unto him who alone is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all obedience, praiſes, honour, and glory, over all, heaven and earth, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I remain a Traveller (in ſpirit) for the reſtoration of the oppreſſed ſeed of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and am your brother, who (in your meaſures) are in the ſame tribulations and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of the Lamb. And unto you, this is the dear ſalutation of my breathing life, in the Bowels of Gods love and mercies. And if in this, my Teſtimony is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, I am content, and made willing (for the joy and reſt that is ſet before me) to lay down the earthen veſſel, which is called</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>WILLIAM BAYLY.</signed> 
                  <dateline>Priſoner at <hi>Hartford</hi> 
                     <date>the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> day of the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> month, 1663.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:41482:20"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
